<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: running | Ward Bekker]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.equanimity.nl/blog/categories/running/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.equanimity.nl/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-28T13:56:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.equanimity.nl/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ward Bekker]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My 5 tips for new runners]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.equanimity.nl/blog/2014/10/08/my-5-tips-for-new-runners/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-08T10:19:32+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.equanimity.nl/blog/2014/10/08/my-5-tips-for-new-runners</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yours truly started running just over 7 months ago with the goal to get into shape. I dropped 17 KG since and now really enjoy running. I even finished my first 10 miles race! (1:21:05). Here are 5 things that I learned in the process;</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Tip 1: Drop weight with this one weird trick</h2>

<p>I dropped 17 KG by running three days a week and eating less and better. Sorry, not shortcuts here. I eat muesli with milk in the morning, a big green salad in the afternoon, and a small dinner with lots of veggies. No food/snack intake after dinner really helped to increase my weight loss.</p>

<p>I tracked my progress and future progress using trend lines in a spreadsheet with graphs. This made my weight goals achievable and predictable, which really motivated me.</p>

<div class="thumbnail"><a href="https://www.evernote.com/shard/s48/sh/21dc30f3-f5a1-41ac-b88b-b40b760a67b0/102f7f87f94c39de4e897876e76a9edc"><img src="https://www.evernote.com/shard/s48/sh/21dc30f3-f5a1-41ac-b88b-b40b760a67b0/102f7f87f94c39de4e897876e76a9edc/deep/0/gewicht.png?width=600" alt="gewicht" /></a><br /><span>Weight graph with trendlines</span></div>


<h2>Tip 2: Buy good running shoes</h2>

<p>I started running in old sport shoes. After 20 minutes running my feet became numb. I blamed the shoes. So I went to a nearby running store and walked out with a great pair of Asics and friction reducing <a href="http://store.nike.com/gb/en_gb/pd/elite-lightweight-quarter-running-socks/pid-754222/pgid-754223">Nike running socks</a>. Never experienced numb feet again. I did get HUGE blisters, as I’m stupid and didn’t broke them in properly.</p>

<h2>Tip 3: Prevent overuse injuries</h2>

<p>After five-ish months of running, I felt super fit, and started to increase my weekly mileage way to fast. Turns out that the quote <a href="http://runnersconnect.net/running-injury-prevention/why-runners-get-hurt/">“metabolic fitness precedes structural readiness”</a> by running coach Jay Johnsen is a correct observation. The overuse resulted in <a href="http://www.runnersworld.com/tag/itbs-iliotibial-band-syndrome">ITBS symptoms</a> and I couldn’t run my planned first half marathon. I stopped running for two weeks, and did a lot of hip strength exercises. I’m now very gradually building up a good base. The goal is a first HM race in the spring of 2015. No more overuse injuries if I can help it.</p>

<h2>Tip 4: Hydrate on long runs</h2>

<p>I ran for over two hours once, which was really an achievement for me, but didn’t hydrate properly. So, I totally crashed afterwards. My body was telling me to put some water and salt in it. I did, an after an hour I felt much better. The next day I ordered the <a href="http://www.nathansports.com/hydration/hydration-belts/trail-mix">Nathan Trail Mix hydration belt</a>, and I never go out on a long run without it since.</p>

<h2>Tip 5: Run negative splits</h2>

<p>My best long runs start with a easy pace (~5:30 min/km for me). After a few KM’s I very gradually step up the pace and finish strong with a fast pace (4:40-50 min/km). In running slang this is called a <a href="http://www.runnersworld.com/race-training/positives-negative-splits?page=single">negative split</a>. In my limited race experience, I noticed that a lot of folks go out way too fast in the beginning of the race and they have a extra hard time towards the end of their race. With a negative split, you better distibute your energy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
